<acknowledgements xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
                  xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
                  xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
                  xml:id="VDG-ACKS" version="5.0">

  <title>Acknowledgments</title>

  <para>
    This book wouldn't have been possible without the gracious advice,
    support, and patience of several individuals.
  </para>

  <para>
    Andrew <quote>Hoss</quote> Butcher. You're a badass friend. A+
    roommate as well, would live with again.
  </para>

  <para>
    Thanks to John Eckersberg and Chris Venghaus for copious amounts
    of feedback early on. It really helped to stoke my fire and get
    things moving. And a special thanks to Chris for being my biggest
    word-of-mouth referral. I have no idea how you meet all these
    people with burning needs to have their virtual disk questions
    answered, but I'm glad you refer them to me when you do.
  </para>

  <para>
    Jorge Fábregas, you were a fabulous unexpected resource when most
    of the major writing was happening for this book. Thanks for
    repeatedly reaching out to me with your feedback and suggestions
    and pointing out errors. This book is better because of your
    unique contributions.
  </para>

  <para>
    Thank you Jon Connell, Henry Graham, and Jyoti Sabharwal for
    editing! Jason Hibbets and Christopher Negus, thanks for the
    reviews, and general authoring and publishing advice.
  </para>

  <para>
    Obligatory shout-outs to Norman Walsh, the man I consider the
    living personification of DocBook XML

    <footnote>
      <para>DocBook Homepage: <link xl:href="http://www.docbook.org/"/></para>
    </footnote>

    , and Bob Stayton, author of DocBook XSL: The Complete Guide

    <footnote>
      <para>Read DocBook XSL: The Complete Guide online at <link
      xl:href="http://www.sagehill.net/docbookxsl/index.html"/></para>
    </footnote>

    .
  </para>

  <para>
    Thank you Wikipedia contributor MistWiz for creating the original
    image, <xref
    linkend="VDG-Appendix-Disk-Drive-History-Illustration-Figure"/>,
    used in the appendix. Also, thanks to Wikipedia contributor Heron2
    for making later updates. The disk components image featured in
    this book has subsequent changes I personally made. Image used and
    remixed according to permissions detailed in the Licensing section
    of the image's Wikipedia page

    <footnote>
      <para>Original Disk Components Image: <link xl:href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:Disk-structure2.svg"/></para>
    </footnote>

    .
  </para>

  <para>
    To my wife, Alicia, thanks for making me so happy and keeping me
    sane. Thank you for encouraging me to work on this book when I
    didn't want to. And, thank you for <firstterm>everything
    else</firstterm>.
  </para>

  <para>
    Finally, my biggest <quote>thanks</quote> goes to David Krovich. A
    mentor, friend, and button-pusher for many years now. You always
    encouraged me to be better than I was. Without the opportunities
    you offered me, and the radical influence you had on my life, this
    book would never have even reached conception. Truth be told,
    <xref linkend="VDG-Cookbook"/> section is mostly a merge and
    refresh of a lot of the notes I took, and staff documentation I
    wrote, working on one of our provisioning projects. Those notes
    became the first chapters of this book.
  </para>

  <para>
    It was while working under your instruction that I discovered my
    passion for documenting everything I learned. This book is a
    testament to that passion. Thanks, Kro.
  </para>


</acknowledgements>
