<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xml:id="VDG-Introduction"
         version="5.0">

  <title>Introduction</title>

  <section xml:id="VDG-Introduction-Introduction">
    <title>Introduction</title>

    <para>
      Foo
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="VDG-Introduction-Conventions">
    <title>Typographical Conventions</title>

    <para>
      Bar
    </para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="VDG-Introduction-Units">
    <title>Units and Prefixes</title>

    <para>
      Throughout this book you will see file sizes specified with an
      assortment of units. For example: 42 kB, 42 Mb, 42 GiB, 42 G, 42 GiB.
    </para>

    <para>
      Without an explanation this may seem confusing, random, and
      inconsistent. However, there is a method to this madness:

      <orderedlist>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    The unit used in discussion preceding/following an example
	    is consistent with the convention used in the example
	  </para>
	</listitem>
	<listitem>
	  <para>
	    Without any scope or context, binary prefixes are used
	    (e.g., 1024 KiB, 35565 MiB)
	  </para>
	</listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </para>

    <para>
      For additional literature on why this necessary, I refer you to
      <xref linkend="VDG-Appendix-Units"/>
    </para>
  </section>


  <section xml:id="VDG-Introduction-Feedback">
    <title>Getting Help/Feedback</title>

    <para>
      If you find a typographical or any other error in this book, or
      if you have thought of a way to make this book better, I would
      love to hear from you! Please submit a report in GitHub:
      <link
      xl:href="https://github.com/tbielawa/Virtual-Disk-Guide/issues"/>
    </para>

    <para>
      If you have a suggestion for improving the book, try to be as
      specific as possible when describing it. If you have found an
      error, please include the section number and some of the
      surrounding text so I can find it easily. I also recommend you
      review the suggestions in <xref linkend="VDG-Troubleshooting"/>.
    </para>

    <para>
      If you're submitting an error with an example, please try and
      include as much relevant information about your setup as
      possible. This includes (but is not limited to): your operating
      system and version, the version of the software the example
      happens with, if you are running the command as the root user or
      not, and the exact commands to run to reproduce the error.
    </para>

    <remark>TODO: Add example bug report?</remark>
  </section>
  <!-- <xi:include href=".xml"/> -->
</chapter>
