<section xml:id="VDG-Performance-scheduler"
         xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink">

  <title>I/O Schedulers</title>

  <para>
    Scheduling algorithms, sometimes referred to as
    <firstterm>elevators</firstterm><footnote><para>TODO: Explain
    why</para></footnote>, are methods used by the operating system to
    decide the order in which block I/O operations (read/write) take
    place. Different algorithms exist because no single one is best
    suited for all workloads.
  </para>

  <para>
    A database server would want to prioritize latency over
    throughput, thus making the deadline scheduler an ideal choice,
    whereas in an interactive desktop you would favor the CFQ
    (<quote>completely fair queueing</quote>) scheduler. Workload
    isn't the only parameter to consider when selecting a
    scheduler. The properties of the backing storage device also play
    an important role (SSD or spinning disk?). In a virtualized
    environment the choice of scheduler becomes even more involved
    because you may wish to consider the scheduler used by the
    hypervisor as well.
  </para>

  <para>
    As you can see, the topic of selecting the proper I/O scheduler is
    neither short, nor is it simple. That being said, in this chapter
    I'll attempt to provide you with sufficient information to make an
    informed decision as well as several resources which discuss I/O
    schedulers in greater detail. Together we'll review the scheduler
    options available, the procedure for setting one permanently, and
    typical use cases.
  </para>

  <para>
    This chapter is incomplete. Please come back for updates.
  </para>

  <!-- <xi:include href="scheduler/options.xml"/> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="scheduler/cfq.xml"/> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="scheduler/deadline.xml"/> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="scheduler/noop.xml"/> -->
  <!-- <xi:include href="scheduler/backing_storage.xml"/> -->
  <xi:include href="scheduler/resources.xml"/>

</section>
