<section xml:id="VDI-Cookbook-Query-an-Image-for-Information"
	 xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
	 xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
	 version="5.0">

  <title>Query an Image for Information</title>

  <para>
    How to query some basic information about virtual disks. The tools
    of the trade here are going to be <command>ls</command> to check
    disk usage, <command>file</command> for a quick check of the
    types, and <command>qemu-img</command> for more in-depth
    information.
  </para>

  <example xml:id="VDI-Cookbook-Example-Query-an-Image">
    <title>Querying an Image</title>

    <screen><xi:include href="../examples/cookbook-query-an-image01" parse="text"/></screen>
  </example>

  <note>
    <para>
      These images are freshly created and don't have any information
      on them yet. Both were created to be 10G images.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    The interesting information we can get from using <command>ls
    -lhs</command> is how the files are actually
    sized. <filename>image-raw.raw</filename> appears to be 10G but
    doesn't have any actual blocks allocated to it yet. It is
    literally an empty file. What's good about these RAW disks is that
    you don't need any special kind of tools to know how large the
    disk is internally. The RAW image should always match it's
    reported file size on the host OS.
  </para>

  <para>
    Our QCOW, on the other hand, is being deceptive and concealing
    it's true size. QCOWs will grow to their maximum size over
    time. What makes it different from our RAW image in this case is
    that it already has blocks allocated to it (that information is in
    the left-most column and comes from the <option>-s</option> flag
    to <command>ls</command>). The allocated space is overhead from
    the meta-data associated with the QCOW image format.
  </para>

  <!-- TODO: Link reference to QCOW specification -->
  <!-- http://people.gnome.org/~markmc/qcow-image-format.html -->

  <para>
    The <command>file</command> command tells us immediately what it
    thinks each file is. This is another simple to perform query that
    you can run from any system without special tools. Here we see it
    correctly recports <filename>image-qcow.qcow2</filename>s
    type. Unfortunately, without any content, all it can tell us about
    <filename>image-raw.raw</filename> is that it's 'data'.
  </para>

  <note>
    <para>
      Its worth mentioning that RAW image types will be reported by
      <command>file</command> as "x86 boot sector, code offset 0xb8"
      once given a filesystem label and a partition table.
    </para>
  </note>

  <para>
    Using the <command>qemu-img</command> command we can get more
    detailed information about the disk images in a clearly presented
    format.
  </para>

  <para>
    With <command>qemu-img</command> it's clear that
    <filename>image-qcow.qcow2</filename> is a QCOW2 type image and is
    only 136K on disk and internally (the 'virtual size' field) is a
    10G disk image. If the QCOW had a backing image the path to that
    file would be shown here as an additional field.
  </para>

  <para>
    For the RAW image there is no new information here that we didn't
    already get from the <command>ls</command>.
  </para>
</section>
