<section xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
         xml:id="VDG-Appendix-Disk-Drive-History-Master-Boot-Record"
         xmlns:xl="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
         version="5.0">

  <title>The Master Boot Record</title>

  <para>
    The Master Boot Record (<acronym>MBR</acronym>) is located in the
    first sector of the primary disk drive. The MBR may be up to 446B
    of code, and partition tables may be up to 64B of data. When you
    add in another 2B to record a <firstterm>Boot
    Signature</firstterm> you have 512B, which up until recently
    happened to be the typical size of one sector

    <footnote><para> Seagate.com - Transition to Advanced Format 4K
    Sector Hard Drives: <link
    xl:href="http://www.seagate.com/tech-insights/advanced-format-4k-sector-hard-drives-master-ti/"/>
    </para></footnote>

    <footnote><para>Pixel Beat - Details of GRUB on the PC:
      <link xl:href="http://www.pixelbeat.org/docs/disk/"/>
    </para></footnote>


    . This first sector is referred to by a special name, the
    <systemitem>boot sector</systemitem>.
  </para>

  <table pgwide='0' frame='none'>
    <title>Master Boot Record Contents</title>
    <tgroup cols='3' align='center'>
      <colspec colname='c1'/>
      <colspec colname='c2'/>
      <colspec colname='c3'/>
      <thead>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>Size (in bytes)</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Percent</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Purpose</entry>
        </row>
      </thead>
      <tbody>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>440B</entry>
          <entry align='left'>86%</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Bootable Code (such as <link
          xl:href="http://www.gnu.org/software/grub/">GRUB</link>/<link
          xl:href="http://lilo.alioth.debian.org/">LILO</link>)</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>004B</entry>
          <entry align='left'>0.8%</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Disk signature</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>002B</entry>
          <entry align='left'>0.4%</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Nulls</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>064B</entry>
          <entry align='left'>13%</entry>
          <entry align='left'>Partition Table</entry>
        </row>
        <row>
          <entry align='left'>002B</entry>
          <entry align='left'>0.4%</entry>
          <entry align='left'>MBR Signature</entry>
        </row>
      </tbody>
    </tgroup>
  </table>

  <para>
    In the old days a disk cylinder (or track) was typically 63
    sectors. This would represent one concentric ring of storage on a
    physical disk. Some people believe that early operating systems
    (notably MS-DOS) enforced requirements which dictated that
    partitions begin on cylinder boundaries, or that the OS needed to
    begin and end on a cylinder boundary. Jonathan de Boyne Pollard
    (JDBP) disputes that claim

    <footnote><para>The gen on disc partition alignment: <link
    xl:href="http://homepage.ntlworld.com/jonathan.deboynepollard/FGA/disc-partition-alignment.html"/>
    </para></footnote>

    , saying:

    <blockquote>
      <para>
	It is often believed that disc partitions have to be aligned
	to cylinder or track boundaries. This is not in fact true and
	never really has been. There are alignment considerations for
	disc partitions, but they have nothing to do with cylinders,
	and they aren't mandatory. Operating systems will still work
	with misaligned partitions, just more slowly for some (not
	all) disc unit models.
      </para>

      <para>
	The idea that disc partitions have to aligned to cylinder
	boundaries is nonsense on its face. Millions of people have
	had discs where the first primary partition began on track
	zero, sector one, head one with no ill effect whatsoever on
	operating systems from MS-DOS through Windows NT to OS/2. That
	was, after all, the default that fdisk/Disk Manager on those
	operating systems used for almost two decades. At best, the
	purported alignment requirement would have been a track
	alignment, with all partitions starting at sector one (Sectors
	are numbered from one, remember.) of any given track.
      </para>

      <para>
	But this is not true, either. No version of any operating
	system has actually required this. Even MS-DOS was quite happy
	to have disc partitions starting at sectors other than 1. The
	only things that have required this have been disc
	partitioning utilities. There's been a bit of circular logic
	about this. The disc partitioning utilities enforced the
	requirement because their authors thought that it was a
	requirement, but people only thought that it was a requirement
	because fdisk and the like enforced it. It was what the
	partitioning utility programs enforced — so the logic went —
	so it must have been a restriction. In fact it never was, and
	no operating system itself has any trouble with this.
      </para>
    </blockquote>
  </para>

  <para>
    What we can take away from JDBP here is this:
  </para>


</section>
